<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Dorchester in the county of Dorcet, at the proclaiming of His sacred Majesty Charles the II. May 15. 1660. By Gilbert Ironsyde Batchelour of Divinity, and minister of Stepleton in the said county.</title>
            <author>Ironside, Gilbert, 1588-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1034_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867954</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867954</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168926</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1034[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Dorchester in the county of Dorcet, at the proclaiming of His sacred Majesty Charles the II. May 15. 1660. By Gilbert Ironsyde Batchelour of Divinity, and minister of Stepleton in the said county.</title>
                  <author>Ironside, Gilbert, 1588-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavell at the Staggs head in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168926:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at DORCHESTER In the County of <hi>DORCET,</hi> AT THE PROCLAIMING OF HIS SACRED MAJESTY CHARLES THE II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 15. 1660.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Gilbert Ironſyde <hi>Batchelour of Divinity, and Miniſter of</hi> Stepleton <hi>in the ſaid County.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the Staggs head in S. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168926:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168926:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worſhipfull the Knights and Gentry, &amp;c. of the County of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> that came with Loyall bearts to Proclaim his Sacred Majeſty at <hi>Dorcheſter.</hi> 
               <date>May 15. 1660.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eauty conſiſts more in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of parts then in the exquiſitneſſe of Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for whatſoever this be, if the other be wanting, it begets a deformity. And was it not ſo in your late meeting about the greateſt affair that ever this County or Nation had, the Proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Kings Majeſty? I muſt needs acknowledge, and record it for your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that you did it with all Alacrity, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, and Loyalty; yet an ill choice was made of your Preacher (an intigrall part of that Service) an old man, much decayd in Strength, Lungs, Parts, plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:168926:3"/>of Abilities as well as Books, by the Diſcouragements and Diſtractions of our late Confuſions, and this was not ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; I have but a few things to ſay for him, beſides that he was of their own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing, that there was a kind of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion even in this diſproportion, I mean as to the work in ſome ſort to which he was to ſpeak; for concerning this <hi>Origens</hi> obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is good, <hi>Deus vult ex locuſtis vincere Gigantes,</hi> God will by graſſehoppers over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Giants, as we ſee at this day, and as for him, <hi>Davids</hi> words are verified, <hi>Ex ore infantium fundaſti robur,</hi> God can perfect praiſe out of the Mouth of a weak inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Beſides when <hi>Abraham</hi> entertain'd the Angels, <hi>Senex currit, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor festinat, Puer accellerat, nullus piger eſt in to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia;</hi> The Servant made haſte, the VVife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtird her ſelf, &amp; the old man ran too as faſt as he could, It's the ſame Fathers obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb facs="tcp:168926:3"/>It was ſo when we received our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraign, as an Angel of God ſent from heaven, in that bleſſed Proclamation, <hi>Nullus piger in tota familia,</hi> Every man acted his part with the beſt of his abil ties; the Sheriff proclaimed, the Gentry atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Country waited, the young men diſplayed their banners, the whole Town triumphed, Men Women and Children acclaimed, and the old man your Preacher did run too as faſt as he could; and though he fetcht not with <hi>Abraham a fatling from the herd,</hi> yet with <hi>Mary be brought his young Pigeons, and his Turtle,</hi> as much Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Zeal and Loyalty as the beſt. And now if you ask why I preſent it to you the ſecond time in this dreſſe, being ſo leane, Anſwerable to the time I had, I ſhall not make uſe of that old Gentleman-uſher, or Trapanner to the Print-houſe, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, not to be reſiſted, though this
<pb facs="tcp:168926:4"/>alſo might be pretended, (the more I pitty their Judgments) the true reaſon is that the loudneſſe of my Voice might be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by the loudneſſe of the Preſſe; and that thoſe that could be but ſpectators, for the Noiſe, Croud, and my Defects, may now be readers of the Sermon if they pleaſe; and thereby both retain and renew within themſelves the ſolemnity of that day never to be forgotten. And upon this account, craving your pardons, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for your happineſſe, from under our moſt Wiſe God, and our moſt Gracious and Dread Soveraign, whom God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, be pleaſed to accept the ſervices of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute> 
               <signed>Yours most Affectionately Devoted, <hi>G. J.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168926:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM. 85.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I will hearken what God the Lord will ſay; for he will ſpeake peace to his people, and to his Saints: but let them not turn again to folly.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen our bleſſed Lord went from <hi>Bethphage</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem, they that went before, and they that followed,</hi> and the very children in the Temple, <hi>cryed, Hoſanna to the ſon of David, Bleſſed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord, Mat.</hi> 21.8, 9, 15. This <hi>Hoſanna</hi> is a long prayer in a ſhort word, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending much matter in a few ſyllables, <hi>Ne ſibi blandiantur verboſi oratores,</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaks on another place;) God is not always beſt pleaſed when we make him the longeſt Orations. You may read if you pleaſe this long-ſhort prayer (for ſo I may call it) in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.25. <hi>O Lord, I pray thee ſave now; O Lord, ſend now proſperity. Bleſſed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some will tell you that this 118. <hi>Pſalm</hi> was penned by <hi>David</hi> for the uſe of the people, when he returned victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous from the <hi>Philiſtins;</hi> but give me leave to ſay, when he returned from his long baniſhment from being hunted by <hi>Saul</hi> (another <hi>Nimrod</hi>) as <hi>a partridge upon the mountains;</hi> when the people had proclaimed him in <hi>Hebron,</hi> and <hi>Samuels</hi> unction had taken full effect, as in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5. This appears to me by the precedent verſes, <hi>The ſtone which the builders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed (Saul</hi> and his counſell, which ſhould have been build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but were indeed deſtroyers) <hi>is become the head in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168926:5"/>Corner,</hi> the chief pillar and ſupport both of Church and State. <hi>This was the Lords doing, and it was marvellous in our eyes; this is the day which the Lord hath made, let us rejoyce and be glad in it.</hi> It is therefore you ſee a <hi>Pſalm</hi> of prayers and praiſes; and this <hi>Hoſanna</hi> is a great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation containing both, even the ſame which they commonly uſed at all their Kings Inaugurations. When <hi>Saul</hi> was preſented by <hi>Samuel</hi> with a <hi>See ye not him whom the Lord hath choſen? All the people ſhouted and ſaid, God ſave the King,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.24. and when <hi>Zadock</hi> had anointed <hi>Solomon, they blew the Trumpet, and all the people ſaid, God ſave King Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 1.39. It is ſo here; theſe people look upon Chriſt as the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> therefore cry <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to the ſon of <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is yet more in this <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> and it lies Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically in this particle of the preſent tenſe, <hi>Now, O Lord, I pray thee, ſave now; O Lord, ſend now proſperity.</hi> This <hi>Now</hi> refers to what was paſt, as much as to ſay, we have hitherto been oppreſt by <hi>Saul</hi> and his Agents, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtyled the violent and the cruel man; but now we have a King of another nature, of a better temper, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Save now O Lord, O Lord, ſend now proſperity.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe that hitherto we have had come in their own names, <hi>Saul</hi> was a proud uſurper, <hi>David</hi> the true proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and that by Gods own donation, which is here cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>his name. Bleſſed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how well doth all this ſuit with our preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Is not our <hi>David</hi> returned from his long exile and baniſhment? Have not our Tribes proclaimed him in <hi>Hebron?</hi> No longer hunted by any <hi>Nimrod</hi> we know? Is not this long refuſed ſtone become the head of our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168926:5"/>corner? Is not this the Lords onely doing? and is it not marvellous in our eyes, and in the eyes of all the world? It's ſurely the day which God alone hath made, no fleſh can claime it, we have great cauſe to rejoyce and be glad in it; for we have hitherto been harrowed by proud, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ping Tyrants, this was their name. But now the Lord hath ſent us a King in his own name; a name written in the Law of Nature, the Law of Nations, the Law of the Land. Therefore let <hi>Zadock</hi> anoint him, let them blow the Trumpet, and let all the people cry <hi>Hoſanna, God ſave the King; Bleſſed be he that thus cometh in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope it is not with us as with thoſe people when they cryed their <hi>Hoſanna's,</hi> for the Text tells us that the Prieſts and Scribes were ſo diſpleaſed, and ſome of the Phariſees (never behind Prieſts and Scribes in this kind) ſaid, <hi>Maſter rebuke thy Diſciples, Luk.</hi> 19 39. I hope there be no ſuch Malignant ſpirits amongſt us, if there be (and 'tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble there may be,) for God never did a work ſo glorious againſt which ſome mens hearts were not imbittered, and their tongues viperous; not the Creation, witneſſe the <hi>Manichees;</hi> not the Incarnation, witneſs the <hi>Marcionites;</hi> not the Redemption, witneſſe the <hi>Socinians;</hi> not his Grace, witneſſe the <hi>Pelagians;</hi> nor his wonderfull workes of Providence, witneſſe our Modern <hi>Stotcks, Ranters,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts:</hi> it may therefore be ſo here. But if there be, their anſwer lyes ready in the Text; I tell you if theſe ſhould hold their peace, the ſtones would cry; God would rather give mouthes and tongues to the very ſtones, then loſe the praiſe of ſo glorious a work, or (which is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent,) were mens hearts flints or Adamants, ſuch a mercy as the Son of <hi>David</hi> hath in it heat enough to melt them.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168926:6"/>
            <p>Honoured and Beloved, I appeal to the conſcience of all Mankind, whether this our mercy hath not in it very much of a melting quality, unleſſe it meet with hearts harder then the upper and nether mill-ſtone. To ſee a King, ſuch a King, ſo miraculouſly delivered, preſerved, reſtored, even by an out-ſtretched arme from heaven; To ſee a Languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing State revived, a dying Church quickned; To ſee Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Schiſmes, Sects, Hereſies, Prophaneneſs, Irreligion, Atheiſm, and (which is yet worſe) Satanicall deluſions, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick phrenſies, that dark and thick cloud aſcending from the bottomleſſe pit which hath been ſpread over us theſe many years, ſo ſuddenly to vaniſh and diſappear. And in the room of thoſe ugly Fiends, the choiſe bleſſings of God, like ſo many glorious Angels, Peace and Settlement, Trade and Commerce, Government and Religion, Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be re-eſtabliſhed; To ſee all theſe caſt upon us with the light of Gods pleaſed countenance in a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, if not concurrence. without the leaſt drop of the bloud of revenge; as if <hi>Eſays</hi> propheſy were viſibly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, the <hi>wolfe</hi> to lye down with the <hi>Lamb,</hi> the <hi>Leopard</hi> with the <hi>Kid,</hi> and none to deſtroy in all the holy mountain. And that which heightens all the reſt, to ſee that God hath vouchſafed to ſuch an unworthy people once more a King, and ſuch a King as may ſeem to ſecure all other his favors, a King of the ancient extract from his Royall Progenitors, to prevent future uſurpations; a King born in our Nation, and therefore ſure muſt love the Nation; a King ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in his perſon, more then eminent for his moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent endowments; a King whom God himſelf hath bred and tutored in the ſchool of forreign experience, without the leaſt taint of their religion, or vices; An excellent ſchool for a King, and in his own houſe a ſchool of afflictions, the beſt ſchool any Prince can be brought up in: in a parallel to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168926:6"/>both theſe I think no Hiſtory can afford. Is not all this enough to melt us into <hi>Hoſannas,</hi> that have not put off humanity, and in the room thereof taken the Wolf or Tyger? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if there be any that is otherwiſe minded, whether <hi>Prieſt, Seribe</hi> or <hi>Phariſee, Papist, Jeſuite</hi> or <hi>Sectarie,</hi> God I hope ſhall reveal it to him alſo in due time; But if any be obſtinate, let him be obſtinate ſtill. In the mean time let us doe our duties, and to this purpoſe let me beg your patience; I ſhall not abuſe it I hope with any long or impertinent diſcourſe upon the words of the Text, <hi>I will hearken, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Pſalm is prophetical, and the ſpirit of propheſie ſees as God himſelf ſees, future events in their preſent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtencies. When <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great died in <hi>Babylon</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prediction of the Solar and Lunar trees in <hi>India</hi>) he divided his Empire amongſt his Commanders, ſaith the Hiſtorian, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1. by this means <hi>Syria</hi> came to <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> v. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Syria</hi> was ever an ill neighbour to <hi>Judea,</hi> and <hi>Antiochus</hi> was one of the worſt that ever had <hi>Syria;</hi> no marvel then if there were great lamentation in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> v. 25. for he not only invades the Land, but alſo proudly enters the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, robs it of all its glorious furniture, takes away the golden Altar, the Candleſtick, the Table, the golden ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, all the gold and ſilver jewels and treaſure he could find, v. 21, 22. He that begins will ſacriledge will eaſily ſwallow bloud; ſo did <hi>Antiochus,</hi> he murdered many a man, ſaith the Text, v. 25. He that will not ſtick at Sacriledge and bloud will make little of rapine, oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, perſecution, and a wicked toleration of all religions; no more did <hi>Antiochus,</hi> v. 41, 42. till all the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was covered with confuſion, ſaith the Author. This <hi>Epipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nema,</hi> this Tyranny was very great upon the people of <hi>Iſrael. Credibile eſt,</hi> It is very credible, ſaith a good interpreter, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168926:7"/>our Prophet in this <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſpeaks of the condition of the <hi>Jews</hi> under this <hi>Antiochus:</hi> and firſt he tells what this poor people did in the time of their great diſconſolation; as chickens when the Kite hovers over them fly to the wings of the Dam, ſo theſe hope to be ſafe under the feathers of the Almighty: this was always their manner when they were afflicted, <hi>they ſought him, and ſought him early;</hi> this alſo the Prophet fore-ſees, for he gives us a copy of their prayer, nay he pens it for them in readineſſe againſt the time ſhould come. This is uſuall with Gods Spirit, to provide his people of ſet formes for particular occaſions many years before they happen. <hi>Moſes, Eſay, David, Solomon</hi> did ſo, and our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> hath given us a moſt comprehenſive forme which may ſerve all our occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to the worlds end: So far is Gods ſpirit from brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet formes with lazie ſervices. This prayer therefore muſt needs be excellent for the Authors ſake, and for its own too. For in it they, Firſt, thankfully acknowledge the goodneſſe of God to their predeceſſors; he had been formerly favourable to their Land, he had brought again the <hi>captivity of Jacob,</hi> he had <hi>forgiven their ſins, covered,</hi> or buried <hi>their iniquitte,</hi> and ſo withdrawn his wrath, v. 1, 2, 3. Then they ſupplicate for themſelves, <hi>Turn us, O God;</hi> which is not meant of their perſons by repentance, but of their preſent condition from miſery, and therefore they adde, <hi>O God of our ſalvation,</hi> and releaſe thine anger towards us. According to which the Latine doth well render it, <hi>Reſtitue nos,</hi> reſtore us, v. 4. Laſtly, they adde a moſt powerfull motive after a moſt patheticall manner, <hi>Wilt thou be angry with us for ever? wilt thou prolong thy wrath from one generation to another? wilt thou not turn again and quicken us, that thy people may rejoyce in thee?</hi> Theſe be no ſaucy expoſtulations; as if they would either
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168926:7"/>direct God what to doe, or chide him becauſe he doth it not; but are vigorous exerciſes of their ſtrong faith upon Gods nature and properties. <hi>Reſpicit procul dubio,</hi> ſaith a good Interpreter; Queſtionleſſe the Prophet had an eye to Gods own deſcription of himſelf, <hi>The Lord, the Lord, gracious and mercifull, ſlow to anger, abundant in goodneſſe and mercy: Exod.</hi> 34 6. this was done in private only to <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet by way of Proclamation, as the Text tells us, that all the world might take notice of it. And having thus taught them to pray, he teacheth them in the next place a farther duty, which is to wait upon the Lord for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. Here he changeth the perſon, it was <hi>us</hi> before, in the plurall, it is <hi>I</hi> now, in the ſingular: and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe this prayer was to be their publique or Common-prayer as we call it, (for ſuch the Church of God have had in all ages.) But this waiting on God afterwards is a perſonall grace, by every one ſingly to be acted. Therefore having taught them what to doe in common, he now ſhews them what in particular; firſt what in publique, then what in private, even to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Gods anſwer to the publique: and ſure Common-prayers thus uſed would prove the beſt prayers in the world. And in this our Prophets direction we have theſe three plain points.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1.</note> their waiting upon God for his anſwer, in theſe words, <hi>I will hearken what God the Lord will ſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2.</note> the great confidence and aſſurance they have of a gracious return, in theſe words, <hi>for he will ſpeak peace to his people, and to his Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3.</note> what God expects from his people whom he hath thus anſwered, in theſe words, <hi>But let them not turn again to folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe very briefly, plainly, and in order.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:168926:8"/>
            <p>And in this their attending on God, we may obſerve in what manner they do it, which is with a ſettled, conſtant, perſevering, watchfull patience; all wrapt up in the Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor of <hi>hearkning, I will hearken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have alſo their diſregarding of all other ſayings, which doubtleſſe were many upon ſuch a caſe; ſome you muſt think vented the bitterneſſe of their ſpirits in rayling at <hi>Antiochus;</hi> ſome reviled his Army and inſtruments, ſome even curſt thoſe that being <hi>Jews</hi> yet fell off to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> and his party; ſome lamented even to deſpair, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to ſee it otherwiſe; and ſome again triumphed at it, <hi>So, ſo would we have it:</hi> but ſaith the Prophet, <hi>I will hearken</hi> to none of theſe ſayings, but only <hi>to what God the Lord will ſay.</hi> We have likewiſe the two ſtrong ſupporters of this their attendance, Faith on the one ſide, and Hope on the other, much like <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> ſtaying up <hi>Moſes</hi> hands in the Mount: Faith grounded on Gods power, he is able to doe it as being God; Hope upon Gods immutability, never failing his people as <hi>Jehovah:</hi> They expect, and thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. Should I gather up all that might fall from this plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Table, how many baskets full might I have? but neither my leiſure nor yours will bear it. I will therefore give you but one ſhort rule, which may perhaps take in much of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>That our prayers ſhould not be ended when we have made them: we ſhould not doe when we ſpeak unto God as we uſually do when God ſpeaks unto us; when God ſpeaks unto us, as ſoon as the Preacher hath done the Sermon is ended with us, for we never think more upon what was ſpoken: it is ſo I fear with moſt men in their prayers; when they have done ſpeaking unto God all is ended with them: And the reaſon is, becauſe indeed they are no better then Papiſts in their Prayers, they make it their <hi>opus
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168926:8"/>operatum,</hi> their work, task, performance, exerciſes, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their fancies and expreſſions; as if God had dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated his grace to the work of ſo often, ſo long. I beſeech you doe not the Papiſts the ſame, when they number their devotion by their beades? Be not deceived, it is no paradox to ſay our prayers are but begun when they are ended, for our hearts that ſent them out, muſt follow them to hearken how they ſpeed at the throne of grace. When a Merchant hath ſhipped his goods for forreign parts, he hearkens day and night, inquires of every veſſell that arrives, looks for a packet by every poſt. By our prayers we doe trade and traffique, hold commerce and correſpondency with heaven; Have we not alſo a factor in thoſe parts, a skilfull, carefull, faithfull factor there, even the Angel of the Covenant with his golden cenſer, even our Lord Jeſus, to receive and improve our intereſts by his continuall mediation? Have we not alſo a promiſe, <hi>Ask, and you ſhall have, ſeek, and you ſhall find, knock, and it ſhall be opened unto you?</hi> We cannot therefore fail of returns, if we expect and require them.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps will ſay, <hi>I have looked long, but never the neer; I have prayed and prayed whole hours by the Clock, the whole Syſteme of Divinity at a time, but never had anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider, was not the fault thine own? perhaps the goods were ſhipt in an old, rotten, worm-eaten, leaking veſſell; if ſo, no marvell if all be loſt. Our hearts are the veſſell, are they not old, made of the old man, eaten through with the old Leaven of malice and wickedneſſe, corruptions and luſts? if ſo, look for nothing. Believe not me; but the blind man in the Goſpel; <hi>We know,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that God heareth not ſinners: Verbum eſt caeci nondum illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minati;</hi> They be words of a blind man yet blind, ſaith S. <hi>Austin,</hi> &amp; true too if rightly underſtood; for this blind man
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168926:9"/>means, that God heareth not impenitent ſinners, ſinners that have ſo eſpouſed their ſins as never to be divorced from them: This he might ſee by the Prophets ſpectacle, <hi>When you ſpread out your hands I will hide mine eyes, when you make many prayers I will not hear.</hi> Here is frequency, <hi>many prayers;</hi> here is fervency, <hi>ſpread out your hands.</hi> God will not ſee the one, nor hear the other; the ſhip was rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, your hands are full of bloud, injuſtice, oppreſſion; if their hands, their hearts much more.</p>
            <p>Or went it not out with too much ſail, over-blown with pride, oſtentation, vain-glory, as the Phariſees was, when in the Temple, Gods immediate preſence, he ſcornfully over-lookt the poor Publican, perhaps becauſe he had but little to ſay, but much in little, <hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner?</hi> We muſt know that it is the humble-ſpirited prayer that pierceth heaven, God reſiſteth the proud, and diſpenſeth his favours to the humble and meek. Or was not the weather ill, the waves went high, the tempeſt, as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Jonas</hi> his ſhip, made her ſides to crack? for our hearts are apt to double with God, we dare not truſt him, being, as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it, double-minded; and then mark what follows, <hi>Let not ſuch a man think he ſhall receive any thing of the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Jam.</hi> 7. As ſoon as <hi>Peter</hi> began to doubt, he began to ſink. Or were not our prayers ſuch as were prohibited in the Court of Heaven, wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deſires? theſe may have returns I grant, but with ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, not mercy. Or did not the end blaſt the work? we deſire to have good things, but to ſpend upon our luſts; then we may ask and not have, ſaith the Apoſtle: Nay, were we not our ſelves our own enemies, we ſhould ſeek to God only for God, elſe we ſet our ſelves in his room, and will God anſwer Idols? Or even thoſe good things asked for good ends, yet hurtfull for us; and ſhould a father that loves us
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168926:9"/>give ſtones inſtead of Bread, a Scorpion inſtead of fiſh? <hi>Negat propitius quod dat iratus,</hi> God is many times more gracious in denying then granting: it were no hereſie to ſay that becauſe we are too well, like thoſe diſciples that knew not what they asked, we are bound to bleſſe God more for his denyings then for his givings. Or perhaps we may have returns and not know it; is it not uſuall with Merchants to ſend for one Commodity and receive another? their Factor who lives upon the place beſt knows what will be for their profit; but who is our Agent in heaven will always ſend us what is beſt for us. Or want we not a ſufficient meaſure of patience? a ſurly Suitor looks preſently to be diſpatcht, and therefore is many times laſt ſerved, to teach him more civility. I think I may truly ſay we are commonly more rude with God then we are with men, I am ſure it was ſo in <hi>Malachi</hi> his time, <hi>(go offer it now to thy Prince)</hi> and why not in this unnurtured, barbarous, and preſuming Age? Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God may perhaps deny us for our ſelves, as he did <hi>David</hi> the building of the Temple, reſerving the honour of that work for his Son <hi>Solomon.</hi> If therefore we would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, let our hearts be ſound in themſelves, diſengaged from our moſt beloved ſins; let them be ſincerely upright with God, not ſtarting aſide like broken and deceitfull bows: let both the Requeſt and Ends be anſwerable to him to whom they are ſent; <hi>Ad Deos non niſi casta,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Heathen,</hi> holy prayers ſhould be directed to a holy God. It is therefore a good diſtinction of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> with which I will ſhut up this point, the ſame prayer may be good and bad, ſuch as God will hear, and ſuch as he will refuſe; it may be good for the Petitions, Expreſſions, Delivery, but bad for the mans ſake that ſends it; a Wicked man, nay the worſt Hypocrite may ſpeak a good prayer, but <hi>Impius non poteſt pieorare,</hi> he can never make a good prayer, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168926:10"/>is, pray as he ought to pray. Thus we muſt hearken for returns, and how God gives them is the next thing which the Text ſhews us, <hi>what God the Lord doth ſay.</hi> God the Lord ſpeaks unto us now only by a double Voice; for that <hi>Filia vocis,</hi> as its called, Gods immediate commerce as with <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> is long ſince ſilent, he ſpeaks now, I mean as to mens prayers, by his Word and by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; he ſpeaks by his Word in precepts, promiſes, Threatnings; by his providence in Events and Succeſſes: <hi>Dei dicere eſt Dei facere,</hi> Gods ſpeaking is Gods working; theſe two ſeem many times to us mortalls to ſpeak contrary things, inſtance in <hi>Ahabs</hi> caſe, a day of humiliation is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, faſting and prayer enjoyned, for the diſcovery of a blaſphemous execution of Juſtice; if you hearken what God the Lord will ſay by his Word, he forbids Hypocriſie, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, Subordination, Oppreſſion; if you will hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken what God the Lord will ſay by his Providence, <hi>Naboth</hi> muſt be murdered, his vineyard ſeiſed: hath his Providence anſwered againſt his Word? nothing leſſe, it only ſuffered the Event, for the further hardening of <hi>Ahabs</hi> heart and the haſtening of his deſtruction. Therefore when the Voice of the Word approves our prayer on the one ſide, and the Voice of his Providence gives ſucceſſe on the other ſide, then God the Lord hath ſaid; elſe the <hi>Turke</hi> may ſay, I have prayed againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> may ſay, I have prayed againſt the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and curſt them too, may not both cry out, what ſucceſſes! do you not here what God the Lord hath ſaid? Nay the Legion of Devils might boaſt of Chriſts favour, becauſe upon requeſt they entred into the ſwine, and choked them in the deep.</p>
            <p>This point (Honoured and Beloved) fathers it ſelf too well upon us of this Nation; we have had many days of ſolemn Humiliation and Thankſgiving, and have been
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168926:10"/>thought to have proſpered even beyond our own preſent deſires; but we never I believe conſidered whether Gods Voice in his Word, and his Voice in his Works went toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet it was eaſily diſcerned, for did we not faſt to ſtrife and debate, to ſay no worſe? did we not faſt to ſmite with the fiſt? that is too ſoft a ſmiting; I am loth to name the Acts of Wickedneſs: and when we gave thanks, was it not for Rapine, Violence, the ſhedding of innocent Bloud, and other horrid conſequences of War againſt our neighbour-Nations, nay our own people? we ſhould have hearkned to the voice of Gods Word, forbidding our Barbarous Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, <hi>Even the ſelling the Righteous for ſilver, and the poor for ſhooes, Amos</hi> 2.6, 8. and not have hardned our hearts from the Voice of his providence: take it for a Rule, When the voice of the Word ſpeaks one thing, and the voice of ſucceſſes ſeems to ſpeak another, look upon it either as a Temptation or a Judgment, even a leading to a reprobate ſenſe, it is always ſo when God grants wicked men the wicked deſires of their wicked Hearts.</p>
            <p>Not to trouble you much, it hath been a long time a praying time, the Court of Heaven hath been ſolicited this many years <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> with much Preaching, Faſting, and Crying to; and now let the world judge whoſe prayers have been heard. Can it be denied that God did hear and grant the prayers, ſighs and groans, <hi>hae ſunt ipſiſsimae ſanctorum Orationes,</hi> of the now inſtrument of his glory, and his peoples good, with all them that mourned in ſecret with him, even when he ſeemed to others to be moſt deaf unto them? and did he not reject all their Anti-ſuitors, even then when they thought and proclaimed to the world that they had been heard becauſe of their ſucceſſes? And the reaſon is evident, for were not their prayers contrary to the voice of the Word, to oppreſſe the Fatherleſſe and the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168926:11"/>Widow, a man and his houſe, to ſubvert right, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Juſtice, and rather to Sacrifice whole kingdomes then their own Ambition and Luſt? and were not thoſe others according to the Voice of the Word, that the yoke of every oppreſſor may be broken, that God would judge the world in Righteouſneſſe, and at laſt require the bloud of his Servants? So that put the Voice of God ſpeaking in his Word, and the Voice of Succeſſe (as we ſee at this day) together, they make a full Anſwer from God the Lord out of heaven; and when God ſpeaks ſo plainly, ſo diſtinctly, ſo with an Eccho, Voice anſwering Voice, can men or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels forbear their <hi>Hoſannahs, Bleſſed be he that cometh in the name of the Lord?</hi> When we thus hearken what God the Lord will ſay, we need not fear, for he will, certainly <hi>he will ſpeak peace unto his people;</hi> the next thing in the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace</hi> in this place is the proſperous ſettlement of that Nation, and therefore we are to underſtand <hi>his Pople,</hi> not by way of diſtinction and ſeparation, but the whole viſible State and Church of the <hi>Jews:</hi> For that which is added, <hi>(and to his Saints)</hi> is onely expoſitory, for what are his People but his Saints? and what are his Saints but his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? it is an Hebraiſm worth obſerving, affirming that to be which ought to be; to theſe he will ſpeak Peace, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they wanted it for the preſent; he will ſpeak Peace, therefore they ſhall not ever be without it; and he it is that will ſpeak Peace, and therefore it can come from no other hand; and he will when it is beſt for them. The people of God do ſometimes want Peace. The Moon hath her Wanes and Eclipſes as well as her Light and Glory; and <hi>Eccleſia habet ſua tempora,</hi> ſhe is like the pole-Star, <hi>Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per verſatur; nunqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mergitur,</hi> ſhe is ſometimes aloft, and anon you would think her falling into the Sea. In me, ſaith our Saviour, <hi>you ſhall have Peace, but in the World tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation:</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:168926:11"/>What Peace had <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> for near 200. yeares together, or in <hi>Babylon</hi> for 70. yeares? what Peace had the Primitive Chriſtians in their 10. Perſecutions near 400. yeares, and what our Engliſh Profeſſors in thoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian dayes? I am ſure our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> complaines, <hi>that the plowers made long furrowes upon her back, more then once or twice, yea many times,</hi> Pſal. 129. and we our ſelves have lived to ſee, and feel, and ſmart under this Truth, conviction ſtrong enough againſt Academicks and Scepticks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And indeed, it is Gods wiſdom to have it ſo, thereby to pluck his peoples Lips from the teats of this Earth: the Nurſe puts Wormwood or ſome ſharper thing to her Nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to wean her child; and God doth imbitter our ſweets, and blaſt our bleſſings, to take off our Affections from the things below, the better to fit us to walk with him, and have our converſe in Heaven; for the want of Peace is the Mother of holy Wiſdom, when we are quiet and at eaſe we are like the prodigall having his portion, minding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but travelling as far as we can from our Father into ſtrange Countries, with Harlots and Riotous living; but the want of Peace, the ſound of the Drum and Trumpet, the neighing and prancings of the mighty ones make us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our ſelves, and think of home. Outward Peace alſo begets a kind of Spirituall lazyneſſe; and we ſay to our ſelves with him in the Parable, <hi>Soul, eat and be merry, take thy eaſe;</hi> but when Peace is gone, this lazy humour is gone, and we ſet our ſelves to work again. In a calm at Sea, the Mariners lie ilde upon the decks: but when a ſtorm is up, they alſo are up and are doing, ſome tend the Anchor, ſome guide the Ship, ſome dreſſe the Sailes, ſome pull the Ropes, and ſome ſtand at the pump; it is ſo with our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the time of Peace ſcarce one ſtirs, but when Peace is gone, every one is ſummon'd to his duty, Faith muſt ſteer,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168926:12"/>Hope muſt be the Anchor, Charity muſt dreſſe the Sailes, Patience muſt pull the Ropes, and Repentance ſtand at the Pump. Beſides, we are apt to abuſe Peace when we have long had it more then any other bleſſing whatſoever: We may truly invert the Apoſtles words, and ſay, <hi>where (this grace) doth abound, there ſin doth abound, even</hi> Sodoms <hi>ſins,</hi> Pride, Fullneſſe of bread, Idleneſſe, Drunkenneſſe, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, Uncharitableneſs, Lukewarmneſs, Prophase<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; I cannot ſay they are the Effects of Peace, no more then the weeds in the Garden are the Effects of the Suns ſhining. No, they are the ſpurious brats of our own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt hearts, yet we know they are the companions and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants of a long Peace, whereas Wars, Perſecutions, Afflictions are Gods weeding knifes, to cut off theſe Evils even by the Rootes; thefore ſaith David, <hi>it was good for me to be afflicted,</hi> he means chiefly by the Wars made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by <hi>Saul</hi> and his Son <hi>Abſolom,</hi> the Croſſe of Chriſt ſaith a Father, was <hi>Currus Triumphalis,</hi> his Triumphant Chariot; ſo in its kind is the Croſs of his Children, even Gods fiery Chariot in which he ſets them to triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their ſpirituall Enemies, and ſo to aſcend to his Throne of Glory: and if ſo, it is not onely Gods wiſdom, but his infinite Goodneſs and Mercy, that his people have not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies Peace. I remember St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> againſt <hi>Parmenion</hi> the <hi>Donatiſt,</hi> hath this diſtinction, <hi>Eſt charitas ſeveritatis, &amp; charitas manſuetudinis;</hi> but is it not a diſtinction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a difference, or is not Gods ſeverity alſo many times his greateſt Mercy? Believe it, God is often more mercifull in taking away, then in giving Peace unto his people: me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks <hi>Job</hi> is at a ſtand for which to bleſs him moſt, when he ſaies, <hi>The Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken away, Bleſſed be the name of the Lord;</hi> either he makes them equal, or prefers the taking away before the giving.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:168926:12"/>
            <p>Conſider this all ye that have ſuffered even <hi>Jobs</hi> taking away, Murmur not againſt it, make Gods uſes of it, let it weane you from the world which vaniſheth away, let it lift you up to a more heavenly mindedneſſe, learn holy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from it, for 'tis Gods ſchool, ſhake off ſpiritual ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, or melancholy, as Divines call it, and abandon your former abuſings of this mercy; thus let me adviſe you to kiſſe Gods rod, then who can tell whether the latter end of <hi>Job</hi> may not be more bleſſed then the beginning? for this we know, that though Gods people have not always peace, yet they ſhall not always want it, as long as they are his people, till the Bill of divorce be iſſued out, and <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ammi,</hi> not my people, be pronounced upon them, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps is the caſe of the Jews to this day, <hi>Whoſe deſolation muſt be untill the conſummation, Dan.</hi> 9. as alſo of theſe poor people in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For God loves not the rod as 'tis a rod, 'tis <hi>opus alienum,</hi> a ſtrange work to him, as <hi>Eſay</hi> calls it; it is mercy that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, and pleaſeth him better, as ſaith the Prophet <hi>Micah, Therefore though heavineſſe be for a night, yet joy cometh in the morning;</hi> the ſufferings of Gods people may be great, but momentary, for he is not willing they ſhould be diſcouraged: It was a ſhrewd queſtion of the Divel, <hi>Doth Job ſerve God for nought?</hi> take away thy hedge: this taking away the hedge did fright <hi>Job</hi> from God, yet it did not ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; amaze him; therefore though the rod of the ungodly may fall upon the lot of the righteous, it ſhall not ever reſt there, but at laſt be caſt into the fire. Elſe what an heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning would it be to the wicked, and how would they blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme? when their enemies that ruled over them made them to howl, ſaith the Prophet, <hi>His name was continually every day blaſphemed, Eſay</hi> 52.5. Every day and every day continually they did blaſpheme, what! even his holy name,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168926:13"/>his omnipotency, as God his faithfulneſſe as <hi>Jehovah:</hi> ſee how effectually this works upon the Lord, v. 6. <hi>Therefore my people ſhall know</hi> (experimentally know) <hi>my name, that I am he that doth ſpeake. Behold it is 1.</hi> He will ſpeak peace, but when? There be two Adverbs which I had almoſt ſaid are Antichriſtian when they interpoſe in holy things, the one is the <hi>Quomodo dubitantis,</hi> an How of doubting; the other a <hi>Quando murmurantis,</hi> the When of repining; the one is deſtructive of our faith, as in the Noble man, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7.7. as long as <hi>Nicodemus</hi> kept himſelf to his <hi>Quomodo iſtud?</hi> he could could not enter into the kingdome of God: the other is deſtructive to our hope, as in <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, Should I attend any longer on the Lord?</hi> the <hi>Quomodo</hi> hath almoſt ſpoiled us of all our Religion; for how many nice and needleſs, and therefore fruitleſſe controverſies hath it raiſed? We agree upon Gods decrees, but whether they be <hi>ſupralapſarian</hi> or <hi>ſublapſarian,</hi> abſolute or conditional, we defie one another as hereticks: that Chriſt is in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament all agree; but whether <hi>Con,</hi> or <hi>Sub,</hi> or <hi>Tran.</hi> or after Mr. <hi>Calvins modo ineffabili,</hi> (which ſure muſt needs be beſt) the world will never agree: That Chriſt gave <hi>Peter</hi> the keys no man denies; but whether as he was an Apoſtle, or as a Paſtor, or as a Believer, we moſt eagerly diſpute. So for the <hi>Quando,</hi> it eats even into the marrow of the ſouls of Gods beſt people many times in their diſtreſſes; <hi>Why art thou caſt down, O my ſoul?</hi> ſaith <hi>David; why art thou ſo diſquicted within me?</hi> Not ſo much his ſufferings as the <hi>Quando</hi> of his releaſe tormented him: This caſt down his ſoul, this diſquieted his heart within him, for <hi>hope that is deferred</hi> (longer then we would or expect,) <hi>makes the heart ſick, Prov.</hi> 13.12. Take heed therefore of the curioſity of the <hi>Quomodo,</hi> if you would preſerve your faith; of the intemperance of the <hi>Quando,</hi> of you would not be ſick at
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168926:13"/>heart. I beſeech you obſerve how ſweetly our Saviour chides his beloved diſciples for this <hi>Quando, Maſter,</hi> ſay they, <hi>wilt thou at this time reſtore the kingdome to Iſrael?</hi> they had long dreamed of an earthly kingdome, much as our Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſts doe of their fiſt Monarchy; a carnall phancie too. They thought long to ſit one at his right hand, the other at his left, to be great and glorious princes, to Lord it over the Chief Prieſts and Elders, the <hi>Roman</hi> governour, the Emperour himſelf; for ſpirituall pride is more boundleſſe then carnall, therefore, <hi>Maſter wilt thou at this time reſtore the kingdome unto Iſrael?</hi> they name <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but they mean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: but ſaith Chriſt, <hi>What have you to doe to ask ſuch queſtions? poſſeſs your ſouls in patience, it is not for you to know times and ſeaſons, the Father hath reſerved them in his own hands;</hi> Anſwer enough to ſatisfie the moſt impatient ſpirit; Conſider the Fathers Soveraignty, it is his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative to appoint the <hi>Quando,</hi> and his appointments the Scripture calls <hi>the fullneſſe of time; Iſrael ſhall come out of Egypt the ſelf ſame day that he had determined,</hi> he ſets the very hour; <hi>my hour is not yet come,</hi> ſaith our Saviour: Gods ſet times are his decreed times, and his decrees are ſecret to us; we can only ſay, that as <hi>he will have mercy on whom he will,</hi> ſo when he will; for peace is a creature of his own making, <hi>I create peace:</hi> and according to this rule <hi>Dei, Deo,</hi> it is fit he ſhould diſpoſe of his own. Then conſider the Wiſedome of the Father, and Wiſedome is moſt ſeen in the ſeaſonableneſſe of her Words and Actions, it makes them like Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver, its the the very ſalt that gives them ſavour, <hi>he will therefore ſpeak peace to his people,</hi> when it is moſt ſeaſonable. Laſtly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that as this Father is the moſt wiſe, ſo our moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, and therefore <hi>he will ſpeak peace to his people,</hi> when it is beſt for them.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168926:14"/>
            <p>I will hold you no longer in the generalls of this <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> I will deſcend to particulars; Gods ſeaſons to ſpeak peace are cheifly three: Firſt, when we cannot help our ſelves to peace, when we have tried our Strength, our Wiſdome, our All, and nothing can doe, then God will doe; when the children are come to the birth, and there is no ſtrength to bring forth; when the Mariners in a Tempeſt have tug'd and tired themſelves, even at their Wits ends, <hi>then he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them out of their diſtreſſe, Pſal.</hi> 107. God of all things loves to take his people off from themſelves, that no fleſh, not the moſt Sanctified fleſh, might glory in his preſence; if this were well conſidered, we would ceaſe to eclipſe the glory of our preſent peace by attributing it, as many doe in parties, to our ſelves, with not you, but we, is ours, not yours; fooliſh people! he is neither yours, nor yours, but only Gods, <hi>Qui facit mirabilia ſolus,</hi> who alone without our help doth ſuch wonders for his people; be as zealous as you will for the King, as the Cities of <hi>Greece</hi> were for their <hi>Homer,</hi> but let it be the Zeal of Love, not Envy, of Union, not Faction, leſt you break all in pieces. Secondly, Gods time for peace is when he hath well prepared his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to receive it; all the ways of the Lord muſt be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to make a more eaſie paſſage for his work: that of the Son of <hi>Syrac, Wiſd.</hi> 8.1. may goe for Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Gods wiſedome reacheth from one end to another mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and ſweetly doth ſhe order all things, her ſtrength is ſeen in the work, her ſweetneſſe in the foregoing preparations; it is ſo in the inviſible peace, for it doth not break in ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, abruptly, irreſiſtibly into mans heart, as a ſtrong man armed, it did not ſo in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> converſion, which looks moſt like it, there was firſt a Light, then a Striking to the ground, then a Reproving voice from heaven, to work off by degrees the innate and adnate reſiſtibility, at laſt he was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168926:14"/>ſent to <hi>Ananias,</hi> and ſo <hi>Saul</hi> became a <hi>Paul.</hi> It is ſo when God gives outward peace to his people, he works it <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but withall <hi>Suaviter,</hi> ſweetly preparing their hearts and conditions before he gives it; all their high imaginations, their wellings of pride and animoſities muſt come down, the ſtrong holds of their carnall confidence muſt be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, their Emulations, Hatred, Uncharitableneſſe, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Bloud-thirſtineſs, muſt be much abated, and as ſo many Thornes and Briars which will choak this good ſeed of peace muſt be rooted out, at leaſt in ſome good meaſure, before God will ſow it amongſt them. When men begin ſuits at Law they ſet out with high reſolutions, but when tired with long journeys, diſhonored with ſervile atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances; when Lawyers have ſucked them on the one ſide, and perhaps Judges have been bribed on both ſides, then they will come to a parley, and though with ſome reluctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, embrace peace with both their armes; it is ſo in all wars, ſpecially civil broiles, this therefore is Gods time. Laſtly, it is his time when people will beſt receive it, and beſt uſe it. They will beſt receive it when they will be moſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for it, and moſt glorifie the giver, elſe peace is not given, but loſt, <hi>as pearls caſt before ſwine.</hi> God loves his pearls, and this of peace the moſt ineſtimable jewell of the lower world; better then ſo, as in receiving, ſo in uſing. When God ſees we will abuſe his mercies, 'tis a mercy to keep his mercies from us. We abuſe them when we turn them againſt the giver, making them inſtrumentall to our own luſts; but when there is any hope we will uſe them as we ought, God is more ready to give then we to receive. I truſt as God hath fitted and prepared us for our peace, ſo he will alſo enable us both to receive and continue it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; and this calls me to the laſt part of the Text without any further application, the point being ſo appliable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168926:15"/>of it ſelf, eſpecially in this auditory, in which every one of us is concerned: follow me therefore, I beſeech you, to the concluſion, <hi>But let them not turn again to folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sin and Folly, the fool and ſinner are ſuch common Synonyma's in Scripture, that being in haſte, and tender of your patience, I may well be ſpared the quotations. Many have ſpoken of the ſinfullneſs of ſin, and they have done well, few of the folly of ſin; yet perhaps this is the more neceſſary Doctrine, and more inſtrumental to the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a ſinner. For tell a naturall man what grievous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations his ſins are, alas, the point is too high for him, or he hath wit and fancy at will to plead for his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veds: But tell him that his ſins make him a fool, unman him, ſo that now he doth but <hi>inſanire cum ratione,</hi> he hath but reaſon enough to make himſelf a mad man, this will awaken him, becauſe you deal with him upon his own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. It were therefore worth the while to ſhew a ſinner his folly, I mean the impenitent conſtant cuſtomer to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his own luſts, otherwiſe <hi>Stultorum omnia ſunt ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> we are all fools, for folly is bound up in the hearts of all the Children of <hi>Adam:</hi> But for the ſins of weakneſs, <hi>&amp; quotidiana incurſionis,</hi> the daily inrodes of frailties, if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted and reſiſted, they are not properly ours, though al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with us and within us; they be thoſe other ſinners that be the fools. I will give you but ſome few hints, which might occaſion a larger Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>A fool is a ſimple ignorant Creature, he hath but very little of the Light that enlightens every man that cometh into the world; and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> a Heathen, could ſay, that <hi>Omnis peccans eſt ignorans,</hi> every evil doer is ignorant, I am ſure the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that his fooliſh heart is darkned,</hi> and which is more, <hi>that he is ſtark blinded by the god of this World.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168926:15"/>
            <p>A fool is not only void of knowledg, but withall uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any; put him to School, let him converſe with knowing men, except you can new make his ſoul, or new mould his braines, the fool will be a fool ſtill: <hi>O ye fools when will ye be wiſe?</hi> The Interrogation implies a Negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as much as never. The <hi>Emblematiſt</hi> tells you, that if you put an Aſſe amongſt generous Horſes, that he may learn to neigh as thoſe Horſes do, yet an Aſſe will bray as an Aſſe, as long as he is an Aſſe; and who can infuſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into a wicked heart? nothing but a new Creation can do it; it is that which <hi>Solomon</hi> teacheth in the 22. Pro. 17. <hi>Though thou ſhouldeſt bray a fool in a mortar with a peſtle as Wheat, yet will not his fooliſhneſs depart from him:</hi> pound Wheat in a mortar with the heavieſt peſtle, you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeparate the bran from the flowr; its the ſerch muſt do it. Its ſo with a wicked fool; nothing but the fineſt ſercte of Gods grace and Spirit can ſeparate his folly from his ſoul. A Fool cannot make a good election of things ſet before him, any toy ſhall be preferr'd before that which is of excellent worth, and the greateſt concerment; for a Fools head is a heap of fancies: No more can our ſpirituall fool diſcern things that differ, he will alwayes be ſpeaking evill of good, and good of evill; ſet before him, as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets uſe to doe, <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> which doe ye think he will chooſe? <hi>Solomon</hi> tells you that <hi>the heart of a fool is in his left hand, Eccleſ.</hi> 10.2. he had rather be ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the left hand with the goats, then on the right hand with Gods ſheep. Fools notwithſtanding are wilfull in their choice, til they have wearied themſelves with their bables, you ſhall not perſwade them out of them: and are not wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men as wilfull in their follies? neither parents, nor wife, nor children, nor friends, nor Sermons ſhall reform them, but <hi>he that is filthy will</hi> be <hi>filthy ſtill.</hi> Much like the obſtinate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168926:16"/>Jew, though he lay in a Jakes, yet none muſt help him out, becauſe it was his Sabbath: and our wicked fool, though he wallow like the ſow in the mire of his ſenſuality, none muſt help him out, becauſe it is his Sabbath, his delight, he hath ſet up his reſt there. Though a fool be thus obſtinate, yet you may eaſily cheat him of any good thing he hath, to his very clothes: Such eaſie fooles are wicked men, they have moſt cheatable ſoules, pliable to any temptation, to any luſt.</p>
            <p>A Fool is a very contemptible creature, he makes ſport to the very children in the ſtreets; and our ſpirituall fool is the very off-ſcouring of all things, ſcorned even by thoſe that are as bad as himſelf; its no news to hear one Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard upbrayd another with <hi>Drunken fool,</hi> or one unclean perſon to make himſelf merry with anothers uncleanneſſe. Put a fool into an Office, or Honour, what a ridiculous monſter doth he appear? <hi>As ſnow in ſummer, and rain in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, ſo honour is not ſeemly for a fool, Prov.</hi> 26.1. Perhaps by this ſimilitude of <hi>ſnow, Solomon</hi> alludes to the <hi>white gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> which Princes and men of honour uſe to wear, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the <hi>ſnow in Salmon, Pſal.</hi> 68. or to the fading, mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nature of all earthly glory: be it ſo or ſo, Honour is not fit for a fool; nay its not onely his own, but the places pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment where he is. Snow in Summer, and Rain in Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt are ſeldome bleſſings; it is ſo with the wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, when they rule, its not onely the ſhame, but the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of a people.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Rod and Houſe of Correction are commonly the Fooles portion; and what is the lot of our ſinful fool but a rod, but a rod to ſome purpoſe? it hath but four twigs, but they be ſmart ones, Indignation, Wrath, Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Anguiſh; and a houſe of correction too to ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, even that Brdewell or Beidlam of hell, with the Devil and his Angels.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168926:16"/>
            <p>And now give me leave to ſpeak freely unto you, Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Beloved. We of this Nation have a long time been ſimple, ſinfull, wicked fools. Thoſe that have calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated will tell you that the year 41. was to be <hi>Annus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalis inſania;</hi> the firſt year of the univerſall madneſſe of Chriſtendome. I am ſure then we began to plot contrive, and act our follies with an high hand, to break through all Laws both of God and Man, with the unjuſt Judge, neither fearing the one nor reverencing the other; nothing could reſtrain us, no not oaths themſelves; then began Perjury to be the great ſin, which all our nice and new-minted gloſſes will I fear never be able either to heal or plaiſter. We were alſo obſtinate in our follies, nothing could take us off, not the voice of Gods word, not the perſwaſions of the wiſeſt men, not the cryes of the people, nor the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of our own conſciences. We were highly pleaſed with our wicked Chymera's, they were our Sabbaths, we had ſet up our reſt in them. Let me adde, what cheatable fools we have been, I doe not mean of our Eſtates, though this be true, but of thoſe precious Gems, Laws, Liberties, Religion, Chriſtianity, Humanity it ſelf; ſuch groſſe fools have we been, and therefore God hath juſtly ſent us to the houſe of correction of theſe late wars and oppreſſions; till now at laſt of his own free mercy and moſt infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he hath releaſed us, yet upon baile, even the caution of the Text, <hi>But let them not, &amp;c.</hi> It is both a caution and a threatning, and it looks more like a threatning then a cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for it's a But with an Apoſiopeſis, <hi>Let them not.</hi> If they do— The folly that is here ſpoken of is nationall, not perſonall; for when do we read that private men did draw down publick judgments upon a nation, except that nation made them its own by law or connivance? God will ſpare great wicked places for a few righteous, therefore he will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168926:17"/>not deſtroy great countrys for a few wicked ſinners. Briefly, the ſins of the Jews that brought this fury of <hi>Antiochus</hi> upon them, may be reduced to theſe two heads. Firſt, the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> was let fall to the ground. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the publick worſhip and government of the Church, was quite changed from what God had eſtabliſhed, the Prieſt-hood was taken from the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> as the Scepter was departed from the Tribe of <hi>Judah:</hi> they might be neceſſitated perhaps to this latter, by the riſing and breaking of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Monarchy, but the former muſt needs be from their own pride, faction and emulation, and this brought in <hi>Antiochus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have ſeen their follies, and in them we may ſee our own, which ſure in generall was great and manifold, of the Court, City, Clergy, Country; we were generally a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple laden with iniquity, yet he that drunk deepeſt of the Cup, was, I think, the moſt innocent perſon. Should I rake into the ſink of all our follies, I ſhould preſent you with a tedious and offenſive inventory, leſſe pertinent to my Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern and Text: I will therefore keep cloſe to both, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, as it was with them, ſo it was with us: <hi>The Scepter was departed from Judah, and the Prieſt-hood from the Tribe of Levi; Every one that could, made himſelf a King, and every one that would, made himſelf a Prieſt.</hi> The Roman Legendaries tell us of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, who in a Viſion ſaw the two lay Mendicant Preaching Fryers, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minick,</hi> and <hi>Francis</hi> upholding his Latterane; and our lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifted Brethren that did but think themſelves ſo, or had the boldneſſe to ſay they were ſo, made our Church a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> and upheld our confuſion: by this I ſee two men run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in oppoſition one from another, may meet at a point in the <hi>Antipodes, Non est Sacri alicujus Ordinis pradicare Evangelium.</hi> It belongs not to men in holy Orders to preach
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168926:17"/>the Goſpel, ſay ſome Papiſts, and the worſt of Papiſts, the <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> and <hi>Non eſt Sacri alitujus Ordinis;</hi> It belongs not to men in Holy Oders (Such are Anti-chriſtian and <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts) to preach the Goſpel, ſay ſome Proteſtants, but the worſt of Proteſtants, the Sectaries; therefore as it was with them, ſo you ſee it was with us, and then came in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus;</hi> in a word, thoſe two Staves which God had Erected among them, for his own Glory, and their Protection, the Staffe of Beauty, and the Staffe of Bands were broken, as it was with them, ſo it was with us, and then came in <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bands I am ſure were broken by Faction and Schiſme, Brotherly union in matters of Gods Service was quite gone, for there aroſe a generation of men, skilfull to ſpeak E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of Good, that blanded whatever pleaſed them not, (though never ſo lawfull) for Superſtitious and Idolatrous; little remembring that to condemn for ſuch, which indeed is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch, is to make our ſelves Superſtitious and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous.</p>
            <p>Beauty was alſo broken, our government was ſhiver'd to pieces, we diſliked what was preſent, and therefore made long Preparations, and ſtrong Combinations for a Change, and a Change we muſt have; though by an honeſt Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was the contradiction, To this purpoſe two things muſt be done, the one taught by <hi>Machiavel</hi> to beſpatter our Governours, even to the ſlandering of the Footſteps of the Lords Anointed; the other was the Devils Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Liberty of Conſcience muſt be pretended from all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws: but who knows not that though humane Laws do not bind the Conſcience, yet the Conſcience is bound to humane Laws; for he that hath ſaid by S. <hi>James, There is but one Law giver,</hi> hath likewiſe ſaid by S. <hi>Paul, You must be ſubject not only for fear, but for Conſcience ſake:</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:168926:18"/>Had humane Laws bound the Conſcience, the one could not have ſaid, <hi>There is but one Law giver;</hi> and had not the Conſcience been bound to humane Laws, the other could not have ſaid, <hi>Not only for fear but for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Laſtly, all this was fallaciouſly coloured over with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Titles of Gods cauſe, and the Goſpels purity. Our caſe you ſee was well like theirs, our Pride as great, our Emulation and heart-burnings greater, our Diſſimulation both with God and Man greateſt of all, and why might, not <hi>Antiochus</hi> come in? Theſe you will ſay were Cleargy ſins, but thoſe of the Layety were not inferiour, nay the very ſame; But what do I? I promiſed not to rake into the ſink of theſe Follies, and ſurely I have gone no further then of neceſſity I muſt, to the ſatisfying of the Text, and my own duty; for had I not ſhewed our Follies, how could I have forewarned you, not to turn again unto them?</p>
            <p>To return again unto our Follies, when we have not only ſeen them, but ſo lately and deeply ſmarted for them, is the greateſt Folly in the World: Every child that hath been burnt will dread the fire, ſhould not men do ſo? the reaſon of the difference is, the child continually ſees the fire, and remembers its burning, but we forget the Judgements of God as ſoon as they are removed out of our ſight; O Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, remember that Gods quiver is full of deadly Arrowes, though theſe be gone, he hath heavier Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſtore for us; if forgetting what is paſt, we return again to our former Follies, Chriſt you know told him ſo in the Goſpel; <hi>go ſin no more leſt a worſe thing fall unto thee,</hi> ſin no more, not Abſolutely, but Relatively; the ſame which now thou haſt ſinned; the ſin of Unthankfulneſs to him that ſo graciouſly had forgiven thee: Briefly, therefore, the Folly of returning again appeares in theſe two things. Firſt, in the guilt contracted, for if you believe the Schools,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168926:18"/>and you may, for its grounded on theſe words of Chriſt; a returning to ſin paſt over and forgiven, puts new life into that very ſin, and makes us doubly guilty in the ſight of God, at leaſt unto Temporal Judgements. Secondly, in the difficulty of a ſecond pardon to be obtained, (for that ſuch cannot be forgiven is the <hi>Novatian</hi> Errour,) becauſe by ſuch returnings our minds are more darkned, the light of Gods grace is more diminiſhed, the will is more depraved, the heart more hardned, the conſcience nearer to be defiled and ſeared; ſuch returnings muſt needs grieve Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and if the greater care be not had, quench it: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though God can eaſily forgive our greateſt Follies, yet not our returnings again unto them. It is ſtoried of a Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee in <hi>Rome,</hi> that he barbarouſly ſlew his Servant even in the preſence of the Emperour whom he entertain'd at a Feaſt, becauſe he threw down unawares a Cubbord of his curious Glaſſes; it ſeems he eſteemed more of his fine Glaſſes then of the precious bloud of a man: Our National Follies which you have heard were like curious new-fangled glaſſes, but will you eſteem theſe glaſſes more then the bloud of men, of a Nation, of your own ſouls? Let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, as many as be well-wiſhers to our peace, and this preſent ſolemnity, in Gods name and the Kings, in the name of the Church and State, for your own ſakes, your wives and children, and your native Countries ſake, turne not againe to your former follies, but lay aſide all faction, diſ-affection, all emulation and animoſities, all envy, hatred, malice, uncharitableneſſe, with all our former ungodly courſes, elſe I muſt tell you, you have no part in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and bleſſing of this day. Think not that our preſent peace is a new Patent for future wickedneſſe, or that if we can upbrayd ſome, inſult over others, and drink the Kings Health, till with it our own ſickneſſe, that we are the Kings
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168926:19"/>beſt friends, and moſt faithfull Subjects: No, we are his greateſt enemies, ſuch as doe (what in us lies) betray both him and our ſelves to our former miſeries; and ſo I have done.</p>
            <p>Nor can I conclude with a better Prayer then that of the firſt Text, which is both a Text and a Prayer: <hi>We pray thee ſave now O Lord, O Lord ſend now proſperity: Bleſſed be he that commeth in the name of the Lord.</hi> Long may the King live, Long may He reign, Long may He be a Father to the State, a Nurſing Father to the Church. <hi>Let all his enemies, O Lord, be confounded, but upon himſelf let his Crown flouriſh,</hi> to the joy of his people, and to the glory of his God, and let all the people ſay, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
